Hi, welcome to this week of "Data Analysis to the
MAX()"
In previous weeks we have looked at how
to calculate with formulas and how to
operate calculations
based on conditions. But
this week,
we are going to look into lookup
functions - how to combine data
from this part of your spreadsheet and
that part of your spreadsheet, and correctly
put it together.
And VLOOKUP functions are very, very
popular - you could say they are like
Taylor Swift
of Excel formulas. Lookup functions are
in the top five of the most used
Excel functions,
and this is why it is very important to
know how to use them
and when to use them. So, let's look at
this week's example.
Imagine you are running a hardware store. So, here you have
information that you export from your
register - you can see
what item code you have sold, when
you've sold it and for what price.
And, on top of that register data,
we are going to do some analysis - we want
to know what
items have we sold. So you can see here
the codes, the associated names, the price
we sell it for,
the price we bought it for, the margin,
which is the difference between those
two prices,
and the margin expressed in percentages.
So for this data we want to do
some analysis.
More specifically, we want to know what
turnover do we make
for each of the items that we sell. So we
could do that
like this, where we have the codes and the
names, and then
from the ProductInfo sheet we import -
we directly link
what the selling price is. And then, with
COUNTIF function
we can look at the actual register data,
we can see
what, when, how many items have we sold
of this particular type, and if we
multiply
the number of times we have sold a
certain item with
the price that we sell it for, then we
get the turnover per product
that we need.
There we have it. We have calculated
the turnover per product. So, the first
thing that you see that's a little bit
strange about this formula
is that Excel inputs a link to
this worksheet into the formula. That
happens because,
while we were building the formula, we
moved to a different worksheet
and back, but of course that's not what we
want. So let's first
get rid of that prefix - just remove it,
because it's not necessary,
it just makes our spreadsheet more
complex than is needed.
So the question is now - is our
spreadsheet now perfect? Are we in the
perfect state?
Maybe you have encountered this problem
before, maybe you know
why this is a problem. If you don't, let
me take you through what's problematic
about organizing your spreadsheet in this way.
To show you this, we're going to select
all data in our worksheet,
copy-paste it into a fresh worksheet,
and we're going to copy-paste it as values,
just so you can see
what the original value was, because,
maybe, some things are going to change
if I mess up my spreadsheet. So, just to be
sure,
we make a copy of the original data. Now
let's go back
to our ProductInfo worksheet and do
something very innocent -
we're just going to sort our ProductInfo worksheet,
sorted based on the selling price. You can think:
"Well, sorting something is never going to
mess up my worksheet"
However, if you look now at the Turnover
per Product we see that our Bench
is suddenly worth only 10 Euros where
previously
it was worth 250. And this is because, as
you can see here,
the links are still pointing at the original values,
and even though we have sorted them,
the links haven't changed. So we are
pointing directly
at the wrong value. So what you
should
remember from this example is that if
you make a link
over worksheet it doesn't get sorted, if
you sort
that worksheet with, you see in the
result here,
potential for error. So this is exactly
the scenario
where instead of a direct link we want to use
a lookup function. You'll see that in the
next video.