In previous videos we've talked about
problems with spreadsheets and how to
address them with testing.
But spreadsheets just aren't always the
right solutions -
there are problems that you can come up
with in your
work that are just not solvable with a
spreadsheet.
And those are the types of problems that
we're going to talk about today -
when not to use a spreadsheet. So over
the past few weeks you've learned a lot
about me
and the things I like, like teaching and crafts
beer
but there is one of my hobbies that we
haven't talked about, and that's going to
the movies.
I really like the movies! I even have a
subscription
to the movie theater in my city that I can
go to all movies
unlimited. So this week's exercises will be
all about
a little movie database I've made in a
spreadsheet. Well, we have movies,
the studios that made the movies, the
rating of the movie, so when you can see
it,
the year that the movie has been
released in, and
the type of movie, the genre, so the
action, adventure... And we have
a lot of data.
In addition to the movies in our
database we also have actors
and movies that they have played in. So,
here you can see that Andre 3000
has played
in a Volcano movie. So it is a nice
little database for movie information
that we can analyse. So there are a lot
of analyses we can do on this data.
For instance, we can analyse the
studios that actors have worked for.
We could be interested in the question:
"what actor in our database
has worked for the most different, the
the highest number of different studios?"
So we can get the information in
from a studio with a VLOOKUP,
this should all be easy for you if
you've watched all of the videos.
So we add a VLOOKUP, and we get the
information of
every studio associated with a movie.
And then we can select
all of that data, there it is, we can select
all of this data
and add it to a PivotTable. This
should also
be a piece of cake if you've watched
all videos. So,
we add our data to the data model,
because we're going to want to use a
Distinct Count
to calculate the different
number of studios
that people have worked for. So, here's
our PivotTable,
we drag in the name of the actor, there it is,
and then we drag in the studio,
and we get the number of studios that people have
worked for. And there's one little
thing that we still need to change, it's:
we need to go to PivotTable
properties and we say "we don't want to
have the count,
but we want to scroll down, we want to
have the Distinct Count".
And if this is done calculating... Takes
a while...
Now we can sort and then we can see that
Christopher Lee has worked for the
highest number of different studios, I
think it's 42.
Yes, there it is! It's 42!
So we have a lot of data in our database
and we can analyse it in different ways,
using VLOOKUP and using PivotTable,
we know that by now.
But let's try to ask ourself a different
question:
we would like to know for all of the actors
not the number of studios that they have
worked for, but we'd like to know for
every actor
their Bacon number. I thought Bacon number
was like a very familiar concept,
I did the same exercise in my class, here
in Delft, for 40 students,
and I said: who knows what a Bacon number
is? And, like
two hands went up... So apparently, it's a
little bit of a movie-geek thing, so I'll
explain to you what it is.
An actor's Bacon number is the number of
steps that an
actor is removed from Kevin Bacon. So
Kevin Bacon himself has Bacon number 1,
and someone that has played in a movie
with him, for instance,
Ed Harris in Apollo 13, he will
have Bacon number 2.
Someone that has played in a movie with Ed Harris,
like Nicolas Cage in one of my favourite
movies, The Rock,
will have Bacon number 3, because his
distance to Kevin Bacon
is 2 hops via Ed Harris. So in this way
we can chart everyone who has played in
movies
based on their distance to Kevin Bacon. So
the number of hops, the number of steps
from Kevin Bacon
defines the Bacon number. We should be
able to calculate this information in
our little movie database, right? Because we
have the information -
we know who has played in what movie,
but
how to get this
out? How are we going to process the
information in such a way that we get a
nice little list
of each actor with their Bacon number?
So I challenge you before you watch the
rest of the videos
to try this. And don't try it on this huge
database,
but try it on this little database. We
will put this online,
in the course website, it's just easier
to play with such a little spreadsheet
than with an entire list of
thousands and thousands of actors. So,
please don't watch the next video yet,
download this, play with it, and try to
see if you can come up with a way
to analyse the Bacon number for each
actor. Good luck!