So we are calculating the Bacon number of
bunch of different actors in our
spreadsheet. And
to stay on topic, I want to say: big spoiler
alert!
If you watch the rest of this movie, you
know how to do it. So if you still want to
try it,
this is your second chance - stop
watching this now,
download the spreadsheet and try to see if
you can do it for yourself!
It will really be a lot more fun than
watching me just explaining it.
Okay, you're still here,
I guess you've done your homework, so
let's see how I solved this problem
using a spreadsheet. Here's our database, or
our spreadsheet,
the little version where we just have
a number of actors. So the first thing
that we need,
of course, is to determine who in our
spreadsheet is actually
Bacon. Well, that's pretty easy, we can
just use a conditional formula
where we say: is this actor equal to
Kevin Bacon?
If it is, he will have the Bacon number 1,
if he isn't,
we could say: then you have Bacon
number 0, but that's not
entirely accurate. Actually, the Bacon number
of someone
in step 1, who is not Kevin Bacon, is not 0,
but it's undefined.
There's no way of connecting to
actor. So we
use a little "-" (dash) for that, instead of 0,
which is mathematically just more
accurate,
and it would also help us because
in the rest of the solution we're going to
use mathematical functions
like the SUM and a MIN and if we have 0
in there, it might mess things up. So,
in one step the only one we can reach
is Kevin Bacon, so he has Bacon number 1,
and the rest we don't know yet. So based
on this, we can see how far we can go.
Let's go back to the list of movies
and it's pretty easy to determine now
which of the movies have someone in
them with a Bacon number that's not
undefined. We can just do a VLOOKUP of
the list of actors,
there we go. Of course we use FALSE,
because we're using a direct connection.
Don't forget: select this and hit F4,
and then we can drag this formula down,
and the movies that have Kevin Bacon
in them will now have a 1 after them, for
instance Crazy Stupid Love
has Kevin Bacon in it, so it gets 1. So,
what we would like to do now is
propagate this 1
to the entire movie, so we can see who
else in the movie will get the Bacon
number 2,
because Kevin Bacon is in it. And what
we like to have
in the movie worksheet is a Bacon number
not of an actor,
but of a movie. And we can of course do
that again, with a VLOOKUP,
if we look here we can see who is in the
movie.
And we use a little bit of a dirty trick
for this, because we can use
the SUMIF
function. We just sum all the values
for a given movie and we sum the steps
that we currently have. And if we sum
a 1 and two dashes ("-"), the result
will be 1,
and if we sum just a bunch of dashes
the result will be 0.
So this SUMIF will actually result
in 1 if someone in the movie has a Bacon
number,
and will result in 0 if no one in
the movie is connected to Kevin Bacon.
So if we drag this down,
you see those two movies, Crazy Stupid
Love
and Wild Things, have 1 and the
other movies have 0.
So we are slowly getting there
because we know now in one step
what actor,
Kevin Bacon, and what movies can I reach,
so we can continue this in the second
step. So now we want to have the correct
number,
not just for the Kevin Bacon version of
the movie, but for all of the other
actors
in the movie. We can do this again with
a VLOOKUP -
we're going to go to the movie worksheet,
VLOOKUP,
and we find the associated Bacon number
for the movie, and we can hit F4
and then we can drag this down. So we are
close, but here we have zeroes,
because the VLOOKUP
in the other worksheet, the SUMIF
resulted in a 0, and that's not what we
want - we want to have a dash.
So let's see, if this VLOOKUP is equal
to a dash,
then the result should be
another dash. Oh, I'm sorry if
it is equal to a 0, it should be another dash,
and otherwise it should be equal to the
VLOOKUP
but plus 1, because Kevin Bacon's
Bacon number is 1 and everyone who has
been in a movie with him
should get the number plus 1. So now
we have the right numbers
in the right line for all the actors, and
if we just
get this in in the actor worksheet, we will
have the correct calculation.
So there we go, Step2. What we can
just do
is use another VLOOKUP and we're
going to look for the
actor and now we take that fourth column,
the D column, because there we have -
everyone who has been in a movie with
Kevin Bacon will have 2,
and the others will have a dash. So
this is
almost correct, we see that those
people that have 2 are indeed
the ones who have been in a movie with
Kevin Bacon.
So, it almost works. There's just one thing
that's still a little bit strange, is that
in the second step Kevin Bacon now has 2,
and that's because we went from him
to Crazy Stupid Love and back, but that's
not really fair,
because he already had the Bacon number 1.
So what we really need to do is -
take the minimum
of what we have already calculated and
what is in this
extra step. And you see that in the
previous video I forgot to hit
F4 there, so I've corrected that now as well.
So we see Kevin Bacon now has 1,
all the others have 2, but unfortunately,
because of the use of the
MIN operation, we now get an error
value (#VALUE!).
I don't know why this is, but if you have
2 MINs, if there are in
different worksheets, apparently Excel
gives an error. So we add
IFERROR around it, if we get an error
then we
write a dash, and otherwise we use the
MIN. So,
we have done it - now, for one step, we've
calculated:
1 - Kevin Bacon, and everyone that has
been in a movie with Kevin Bacon now has
Bacon number 2.
We would still need to continue this
entire step
another time if we would want to do it for
three steps and
for four steps and for five steps.
So, can we do this? Yes, we can! You've
just seen me do it.
However, if you continue this calculation,
and I encourage you to try to continue it by
yourself,
then you'll see that for three steps you
will need
8 auxiliary columns, 8 conditional formulas,
3 MINs and
8 VLOOKUPs. So that's maybe not
really what you want
and then you're just at three steps. And I've
looked it up, and apparently the highest
number that
an actor in Hollywood has is 12, so if you
want to continue this calculation for
12 steps,
then we need like 25 VLOOKUPs.
So, probably we're not really on the right
path here,
but it is possible.