So we've calculated the Bacon number in
the previous video
in Excel which is possible but takes us a
lot.
I'm not afraid to admit that it took me
about five hours to come up with this
solution,
and I am quite handy with Excel,
so this is not a solution you want. Actually,
I hope that
in your mind you have something like
this: WIIIIEEEEE, The No Excel alarm!
If in your daily life you're making a
solution
that takes you more and 10 VLOOKUPs
to put together,
then something is off. You should
really be thinking:
am I using the right tool for the job,
is this still the best way to do it? So
of course then the question arises -
what should we use? What is a better tool
to use
then a spreadsheet? What about
programming?
Isn't it easier if you use a programming
language, because with programming you
are not limited to
the rows and columns of Excel, you can
do anything you want.
This might be a good solution for a
problem where Excel is not entirely fit.
However, I'm a little bit like a Hobbit,
I like to stay in my comfortable Shire,
I don't want to leave my
comfortable Excel home, to go to a
programming language that
I'm not familiar with. Of course we could
use VB.
Visual Basic for Applications is a
programming language that is embedded
right in Excel, maybe you've been working
with it before,
and this you can use as a programming
language to
automate your spreadsheets, to
calculate things
that you cannot do with a formula. This is a
possibility, if you have been working
with VBA before,
I challenge you again to try to solve
the Bacon puzzle
with VBA, this should be a lot easier
than using formulas. However, that's not
what we are going to use in this
course.
What we are going to use to automate
our spreadsheet is a language called
Python. So, why Python? One of the reasons
that I like to use Python is
that it's currently the number one
programming language
taught at universities. So in a few years
there'll be lots of people around the
world they're really know how to program
in Python.
It's also quite easy to learn, you'll see
that in
examples in this video, that the syntax,
the way you write in programming language,
is quite easy, and also there's a big
ecosystem around Python, that means a lot of
small Python programs, called libraries,
exist in the world
to solve problems, and if you have such a
problem
you don't need to write in Python yourself,
you can just use the programs
other people have already created. So
these are all reasons
that I prefer Python over VBA, but VBA
is also a good programming language that
you can certainly use for this type of
problems.
But if I want to use Python,
do I have to go away from my spreadsheet
home? You can.
You can use Python totally separate from Excel,
but then you have to do a lot of learning,
you have to migrate your data from a
spreadsheet probably to a text file, so...
I don't want that, I want to have
a Python and Excel,
both of them. Luckily, there is a solution.
There is a cool program that's called DataNitro
that allows you to use Python
in Excel. Much like VBA, you can just
script your spreadsheet with Python.
This solution unfortunately is only
available for Windows,
but there are alternatives for Mac and for
Linux, we'll put links to the alternatives
on the course page. So let's try to use
DataNitro, here you can see it, if
you had a keen eye
you've seen that in the screenshots
of one of the previous videos
there was a DataNitro plugin. So,
it's right there in Excel,
and if you go there, if you go to the
worksheet, let's click it,
if you click Python Shell, you get something
like a calculator where you
can type formulas, like 3 + 5,
much like you can type formulas in Excel,
but you can also refer to
the spreadsheet. You can do something
like C2 + 5,
but you don't do C2 as you do it in
Excel, you have to directly call
the value. So you see,
say, give me the cell on C2, the value,
and add 5 to it. And it's not just
reading,
you can also
write to the spreadsheet, as you see me
do here. Let's put "Hello!"
in A1 and then you see that not just
A1 has changed,
but also all the values that depend on
it. So you change a value and then
the spreadsheet calculation kicks in,
and everything is recalculated.
But let's quickly put it back to Kevin Bacon
because, otherwise, our nice
Bacon calculator is messed up.
So this seems to be a good solution that
might help us
to solve our Bacon problem with Python,
and that's what we're going to do
in the next video.