Hi, Felienne!
- Hi...
So nice to see you!
- What a surprise that you would call me.
Felienne, I have always said it: you are one
of my favorite employees and I've seen an
excellent dashboard.
It's amazing!
Thank you...
- I have always said we should invest in events.
And now I have seen in your dashboard that
these events are profitable indeed!
I'm very happy to congratulate you:
You are now the head of the events team.
Thanks, thank you so much!
If you make a nice visualization
I can present it to the board.
I will, yes, I will definitely make a visualization
so you can present it to the board.
Thank you so much!
Congratulations Felienne and I am
looking forward to receive that.
Thanks.