In the previous video I showed you how to
use
named ranges. They're really nice to use,
because it makes it a lot easier,
to read your formulas. However, there is still
an open challenge,
because we want to be able to add new
teachers to our worksheet
without having to update either the formulas
or the named range. So if we would like to
add for instance myself, I'm going to
moonlight as a dance teacher,
I want those formulas to be updated automatically
and our current solution of using an
entire column as a named range
is actually no good, because it blocks
all of the cells
underneath the data. So in this video I'm
going to show you an alternative
solution
that will address both of these problems.
We can select
our data. Let me remove myself, I will
re-add myself later.
Now we can select all the data
in our worksheet and we can insert
a data table, insert table right
there.
And then Excel asks us to select what data
we would like in the data table
and also whether or not our data has
headers, whether the first line describes
what the date means. And first of all, we get
this nice little visualization on top
of our data,
but also what is happening is that all
of these columns are
automatically turned into something
like named ranges,
labeled by the first line, labeled by the
headers,
so we can use that in our formula. We
can say: we want to count
'Table1' and then we get all of the columns in
our table, we want to have 'Table1' -
'Maximum Level', and now the formula works.
And, if we add another teacher to our roster,
let me re-add myself
as a dance teacher, you see a little corner
thingy over there
is going down with the table and that
shows where the table ends.
So as soon as you enter a new row into the
table,
the table is extended and you don't have
to update the named range. So let
me add another teacher to show you
that little table thingy, the corner edge
is showing you where the table ends.
So this is a solution that looks really
nice, we have all the benefits
of named ranges. However, we don't have to
change
anything in case we're adding teachers.
But there's one thing that's super ugly,
actually I hope you have been
shouting at your computer screens again:
"Oh no, I don't like the name of that
table!
How can you have a video about named
ranges, names
with a table that is called 'Table1'? That is
crazy!"
You are right, my friend, that is crazy.
Lets immediately change the name of the
table, because
this is super ugly. We can do that, as I
showed you in a previous video, with the
name manager,
but there is another solution as well,
to get rid of that
ugly 'Table1'. If we go back to the
'Teachers' worksheet and select the data table,
we get an additional tab in the ribbon.
And there,
we can easily change our table without
selecting anything.
And you see that within the formulas
now also we get
table 'Teachers' instead of 'Table1'. We
don't have to
update anything. And there's more we can
do
in this ribbon tab. For instance, we can add
slicers, this is really like a filter,
you see the logo is similar to a filter
but it's more interactive.
You can click all the tariffs you want
and the data table will
update automatically. So this is a nice
little way,
if you have changed your data into a
data table, to interactively play
with what is in your dataset.
And I encourage you, this is not really
an exercise, but I encourage you
to download the spreadsheet from our
course page and to play with everything
that's there.
Because the data table allows for a lot
of playing: you can change the markup,
you can add total columns or total rows,
so download the spreadsheet and play
with it, because it's
really really nice to work with data
tables. See you in the next video!