So, how to manage your spreadsheet? That
is the central question
of this week's video - how to make sure
that that cute little spreadsheet puppy is
not going to turn into
this huge monster, that everything remains
clear and calm
and error-free. So in order for us to dive
into
how to manage a spreadsheet, we're going to
look again at the hardware store.
I hope you remember this example where
we export data from a register
and analyse our sales in a spreadsheet.
So, here's a recap
of the data that is in this spreadsheet - we
have
a list of items that we're selling, we
have their names, their selling and
purchasing price,
the margin, which is the difference
between the purchasing and the selling
price,
and the same margin expressed in
percentage.
So this is really a very small spreadsheet,
there's hardly anything that could go
wrong with such a small example.
So in this sense, it is really useful as a
running example, because it's really like the
puppy.
It's super small, so if we make sure that
while it's still small
it behaves well, it might grow up to be
a responsible
spreadsheet. So, remember also from
the second week's videos that if you
use a link,
for example, in a spreadsheet, a direct
link to another worksheet,
if you start sorting the links,
everything gets messed up.
So this is a typical risk in a
spreadsheet and our solution so far was
just to make sure
that we use right formulas. We know
how to build the formulas, and we know
that if we use an INDEX-MATCH
function
then nothing goes wrong; that even if
you sort the other part of your
spreadsheet then
still you get the right results. However,
remember that
many things in your spreadsheet can
go wrong.
This is just one example, there are so
many things
that could potentially go wrong - maybe
you input the wrong
value, maybe you used the wrong formula,
maybe you miss copy-paste and you
copy-paste your data
in a wrong part of the spreadsheet... And it's not
just you, you're not the only one working
with the spreadsheet - in a typical
situation
12 different people are
working with one spreadsheet. So maybe
you know what to do after you follow
this MOOC,
but does everyone else involved in your
office in the spreadsheet?
If you send your spreadsheet to someone
from Sales, will they also know what
formulas to use?
So everything in this week's videos is
about how to keep our spreadsheet safe,
how to keep that spreadsheet safe and
keep the
bad influences out. Wrong inputs,
wrong formulas,
how are we going to protect
ourselves from those bad inputs?
And remember, other disciplines have very
similar problems,
like programming, but also hardware
design, if you build a car,
this car is not going to go on the
highway before it has been extensively
stress-tested. We do this type of
things with cars
before we even allow someone to drive in
them. Other domains use testing
to make sure that whatever they build is
really
well-structured, and that is exactly the
approach that we're going to take in
this week's video -
we're going to stress-test our
spreadsheet and make sure
that nothing can go wrong!