Hello everybody!
Welcome back, in this bonus video.
Until now, we can change the data on the dashboard
using a dropdown list over here.
So, it's now 2016-12, and we can change it
to 2016-07 for example.
And all the data will be changed.
But we also.. In earlier videos we have looked
at the use of slicers.
And it would be nice, maybe not for the period,
but it would be a good technique to know,
is how you can use a slicer to change the
selection of the data in your dashboard.
And normally a slicer is linked to a PivotTable,
and a lot of this data is not coming from
a PivotTable.
So we need a little trick to connect the slicer
to our dashboard.
So let's have a look at how we can do that.
And I have to go to one of my very first slides
over here.
The 'validation,' because here I have a list
of all my periods.
And what I will do is: I will insert a PivotTable.
Oh.. That's not what I wanted.
So we will do that again.
Again, we're going to insert a PivotTable.
But I want to have it located on the existing
worksheet.
That's not something I normally do, so I was
a little bit too quick with clicking.
I put it over here.
There it is.
It's a very simple pivot table.
I will put the period in the rows.
And, I now will right-click here, on the period
field and say 'add a slicer.'
So, now we have a slicer.
If I select the value, it's linked to the
PivotTable.
In this use case, I'm only interested in one
period that's selected.
That will always be this position in the pivot
table.
So I'm going to give this cell a name.
I will call it 'pivotPeriod.'
There we are.
And I will copy the slicer, and let's go to
our dashboard.
So here we have our dashboard.
I will copy our slicer.
And first I'm going to change the formatting
of the slicer a little bit.
I want it to have two columns.
There we are.
Make it a little bit longer.
That's a bit too long.
There we are.
I can make it a bit..
I'm happy with that.
Now, over here I say: 'the value in this field
should come from the field pivotPeriod, that
we have just created.'
And that is linked to our PivotTable, and
our PivotTable is linked to the slicer.
And now we can choose any period in our slicer,
and the dashboard will adjust.
So this is a very easy and low-tech way to
link a slicer to a specific cell in an Excel
formula.
So, that's the first bonus video.
In the next one we still have a little problem.
And there we need to dive a little bit, only
two lines, into VBA to get our target there.
So, I hope that you're very interested now.
And that I'll see you in the next bonus video.