Welcome back everybody!
In the very last bonus video of this series.
In the previous bonus video we created a slicer.
And now we can use the slicer to select the
period we want, to look at the data.
And the data will change accordingly.
But there is one problem with it.
And the problem is with the top-ten lists.
Because the top-ten lists are based on a PivotTable.
And we really need that, because we have a
lot of customers, so we really need the PivotTable
to summarize for us what are the top-ten customers.
And the same for the products.
But if I change the selection of the period,
then it will look up additional data.
You can see that the trend, the sparklines,
are changed.
But it did not refresh the PivotTable.
To do that I need to go to 'data.'
I should not select a picture.
I should go to 'data.'
And then I say 'refresh all.'
And now on the background it will also automatically
refresh the tables.
And we saw some changes over here.
I don't like that.
I would like to automate that.
There is no way to do that with a formula.
But we can do it with VBA.
And it's not that difficult.
So, because it's a bonus exercise, we should
try to do that.
We need to go into the VBA editor, and we
can do that with key combination 'alt+F11.'
So, here we are in the program environment
of Excel.
And here we see our VBA project with our worksheet.
Now, what we want to do is that as soon as
this field, this cell, X1, as soon as that
is changed we want that the PivotTables are
automatically refreshed.
And we can do that by using an 'event.'
And it's an event that should be triggered
by the sheet 'dashboard.'
Where is it..
There we are.
So we double-click on it.
Then I say it's a 'worksheet event.'
The first one is always not the one I want.
Because this is a 'selection change.'
Meaning [an] event that will be triggered
as soon as we click (with the mouse) somewhere
on a cell.
But we only want to have an event triggered
if a value in a cell in changed.
And therefore we need the 'change' event.
Meaning that this one we can delete.
So what we see now is a..
We have an event, so every time a cell is
changed on a worksheet, on the worksheet 'dashboard,'
this event is called, and we will get a 'target.'
And the target is the cell, or the range of
cells that has been changed.
So what we could do is, we could create an
'if' statement.
'If target.Address = "$X$1"', because that
was our cell.
Then, you should do something.
And an 'If' should always be closed with an
'End If.'
So, every cell can be changed, but only if
it is X1, then the PivotTable should be changed.
Now, to do that the PivotTables are located
on a sheet 'CustT10' and 'ProdT10.'
And what will make our life a little bit easier,
if we give the PivotTable that we see over
here a proper name.
So let's do that.
Because normally it is called something like
'PivotTable 1,' but now we're going to say
this is the Pivot..
No, I'll just call it 'Top10Cust.'
And I'll do the same for the product PivotTable.
With the exception that the name will be a
bit different.
'Top10Prod.'
So now I have two named PivotTables, and that
makes our coding a bit easier.
And they're located on the sheets 'CustT10,'
and 'ProdT10.'
We go over here and we say we have the sheet
'CustT10.'
And on that sheet we have a collection of
PivotTables.
Or, we at least could have a collection of
And from that collection of PivotTables we
want to have the 'Top10Cust.'
And from that specific PivotTable we want
to do a refresh of the table.
And if we have that we can copy it.
And now we have to change it for the 'Prod.'
And this should do it.
So we need 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 lines of code,
with the core only being two lines.
Let's check if we did not make any errors.
We did.
And that is correct.
It should not be 'Sheet,' but it is a collection
of sheets, so we need an 's' there.
Check again.
Yeah, no trouble, no error messages.
Then I'm always very curious if it works.
So I'll put a break-point over here.
So that I'll really see that it will go into
this code.
And actually, I should put it over here.
We go to our dashboard.
And now I'm going to change to 2016-12.
And, dang, it is in our code.
We can see that the address is X1.
And then I have an error over here..
I see it.
So we will continue.
And it did work.
So let's remove the break-point.
Let's go back and do a final test.
So we're going to change it back to 2016-07.
And now you see the system needs a little bit more
time, but it did not only refresh all the
data, but it did also refresh the sparkline
data.
We have a small problem over here, but that's
an error in my own file.
In the file you can download you won't have
that problem.
So, that brings us to the end of this exercise.
I hope you enjoyed it.
I hope to see very nice dashboards from all
of you.
Thank you!