Hello everybody!
Ready for our next chart?
We're going to look at the average order size.
Maybe you remember for last week that there
are three basic charts.
We have a bar chart, or column chart.
We have a line chart, and we have a scatter
[plot].
The scatter you won't see in the dashboard.
The reason is that this is a business dashboard,
and normally we do not use a scatter plot
a lot, because we do not have to explain relations
between objects or variables.
So we started with a bar chart, and now we
go to the next basic chart, which is the column
chart.
It's going to be the 'average order size.'
I would take a short moment to look at the
x-axis.
There we see the periods, and the periods
consist of 2015-06 to 2016-06.
And there are two things notable.
That you do not need to repeat (for every
label) the year.
If you start with the year and end with the
year it is very clear for the reader that
these are months in a year.
And you save a little bit of space.
Because what I don't want to see is text that
is vertically aligned or that is rotated.
I just want to have normal, plain text.
The second thing you see is: if you ask people
to make some kind of trend overview, they
normally will select twelve periods.
Because that's a whole year.
What I did over here, and what I did in every
trend chart in the dashboard, is: I selected
13 months.
And the reason that I do that is that if I
choose 13 months I can compare this year with
last year.
And that is what you see in the chart.
You see 2016-06, and we can compare it with
2015-06.
So that's a small tip: use 13 periods.
Now let's see how we can create that ourselves
in Excel.
We need to have the 'average order size.'
Here is the raw data.
Just a very quick moment, because what you
remember (maybe) from the chart, is that in
2015-06, there was a hard return.
And this is the way how you do it.
I have the year, I have the month, and in
between I put character 13, which is a hard
return.
And that makes it possible to get the year
on one row and the period on the other row.
The rest is easy.
So here I have my data.
I want to have my average order size.
So I'm going to select that.
My normal strategy for creating a chart is
just select the data, and then insert the
graph, or the chart.
And in this case I want to have a column chart.
Again 2D.
And here it is.
And I made a little mistake, so we're going
to delete that, because it would be nice if
we instruct Excel what should be the x-axis.
That should be the periods.
And then I use the 'ctrl' button again, and
the 'ctrl' button is playing tricks on me today..
There it is.
So now I have the two ranges.
One for the x-axis and one for the average
order size.
I say insert, column chart, column, and there
we are.
And I see that now I have a nice x-axis.
First thing that I notice is that I have my
title again.
I will remove it.
I still don't like the whitespace, so we're
going to change that to 75%.
Actually, what I should have done, also on
the other chart, is I should make it a little
bit smaller.
Because we really have to fight for space
on our dashboard.
So normally I make it 8 points.
I don't need the grid lines.
And I don't want to have a fill.
So most of the times we are changing the same
things.
I don't want to have a fill.
To be sure, I don't want to have a border,
because sometimes if I leave it on automatic
Excel will add it.
Now, I still remember the dimensions of my
chart.
So I'm going to change them.
They were 2.15 by 2.27.
And it should be the right format.
Now, it's still a bit crowded over here, in
the x-axis.
So, what I could do is..
So I selected it, I can check that I selected
it over here.
And now I can say that I want to have my labels
on a specific interval, which is three.
Which makes it less crowded.
And I think I'm quite happy now with my chart.
So I'm going to copy it.
Go back to my dashboard.
And it can go next to our previous chart.
We will specify that it is the order sizes
in '1 X $',
and we have to say that this is the 'average
order size.'
There we are.
OK, so that was the average order size.
So we have the 'sales by category', we have
the 'average order size.'
We have two of our charts, but you see we
have still a lot of empty white spaces.
In the next video we're going to have a look
at the 'sales trend.'
We're going to have a new chart type.
See you then!