Hello everybody!
Welcome back.
We're going to have a look at the next chart.
That is the a combined chart.
It is the sales trend.
We have a line chart and a we have a so called
area chart.
So, let's have a look in Excel how we're going
to create that.
We go to the right tab, with the data.
We need the sales trend.
Here we are.
And we're going to do the same as last time.
We're going to select the data we need.
This time I don't need my 'ctrl' key that is nagging me.
I can just select everything I need.
So I have my x-axis data, my actual data,
and my budget data.
And we say 'insert', and we're going to insert
a line chart.
Over here.
2D line.
So, here we have the data.
First, we will clean it up a little bit.
Delete the title.
I don't need the legend.
In the last video we will focus on what to
do with a legend.
But we don't need it on every chart.
So we're going to delete it.
For once I will leave the grid lines over
here.
But this line, which is the budget line.
And I can see it over here.
I like that to be an area chart.
So I select it, I use my right mouse-button,
and I say 'change the series chart type.'
And we're going to change that to an area
chart.
There we are.
But now it also changed this one.
This should still be a line.
Here we are.
I changed it for the two [of them] at the same
time.
This is what we want.
I don't like the colors, so I'm going to change
the color a little bit.
Normally it would be a light blue, but to
make it a little bit easier to see it in the
video I will change it to a color that I don't
like but is clearly visible.
And that is.. this one.
And I want to have this in a different number format.
Although, now I think that this is OK.
Let's check our master.
Yeah, this is OK.
We want that in thousands.
We do have that.
Than we just have to change the format to
2.15 by 2.27.
There we are.
I should change the font over here.
Otherwise I get text in an angle, and I don't
like that.
I will do the same for the vertical axis.
And we should reduce the number of labels
a little bit over here.
I'm going to format the axis.
We say we want the labels.. make it consistent
with the other one.
We want to have it only [every] three times.
And then we should get rid of any fill and
any border.
We will cut it.
Go to the dashboard and I think the sales
trend should go over here.
There we are.
And I will call it 'sales trend.'
And I will do it here in the chart title.
Sales trend.
And in this case it is really important that
we say something about the number that people
see.
It's '1000 x $.'
So, there we are.
So, we're back at our overview.
Three charts are filled now.
Let's have a look what the next video will
bring us.
It's a new type of graph.
It's a thermometer graph.
And it's a little bit different that what
we saw until now.
So I will see you in the next video.