Hello everybody!
Welcome back.
In this video we're going to look at new chart
type.
Actually it's a chart we already know.
It's a column chart, but we use it in a very
special way, so that we very easily can compare
actual and budget in just one column.
So, it looks like this.
And let's see how we can create this in Excel.
So, we're back in our dashboard.
We go to the 'sales' slide.
Almost no data, because we only have two numbers.
We have the actual sales, or the actual revenue,
and the budget revenue.
That's what I select.
And I'm going to say 'insert', and in this
case, a column chart.
Now, what I need, the trick I want to do,
and maybe we have an example over here, is:
I want to move this one behind that one.
But I can only do that if this is a separate
series.
And now it's one series, with two categories.
So we have to change that.
And you can do this with this magic button.
So I go to the chart tools.
Design, switch row and column.
And if I do that I immediately see that there
are two different ranges.
Now, we're going to change this one to the
ugly but clearly visible color.
There we are.
We get rid of the title.
And now we have to move them behind each other.
And we have to do a trick for that.
I'm going to select the 'actual' series.
Right-mouse click.
Format data series.
And I'm going to say 'OK, you have to display
this series on the secondary axis.'
And now you see they are just behind each
other.
But imagine that my budget would be lower,
then I wouldn't see it.
So somehow, I have to make the actual bar,
or the actual column smaller.
And we can do that by using the 'gap width.'
So I make this one 200.
And I will make this one 50.
So this is kind of OK, but my budget is lower
than my actual, and here it is higher.
And that's because we have two different axes,
and the scale is different.
For years now, I'm waiting for Microsoft to
somehow automate this, but they don't do that.
So we have to do it ourselves.
So I'm going to select this axis.
And I'm going to say the total should be six
million.
And I do exactly the same over here.
So I have new values over here.
And now I have two exactly the same axes.
And now we can see that 'budget' indeed is
lower than 'actual'.
So, this has no function anymore.
We can get rid of it.
I don't need the grid lines.
Get rid of that.
But I don't like these large numbers.
So I'm going to change the number format of
it.
We can do that over here: 'number.'
We say it also in the last week.
We can work with a custom number format.
There we are.
And in this case I'm going to say.. with a
thousand separator at the end.
And actually I need two because I want to
have it in millions.
Now I have it in millions.
I don't need this '1.'
We can get rid of it.
There we are.
Now I just have to adjust the format.
And here we have another trick.
Because if we look at our dashboard, we now
need over here three separate charts.
So it should be a little bit smaller.
It should be again 2.15 high, but now .76
wide.
And I need some kind of axis, so I'm going
to say (over here) that I want tick-marks
outside the major level.
And now I have a very nice chart.
Of course it's still filled.
We don't want that.
We want to control that ourselves.
So we change that.
And we cut that.
And we're going to paste that in our dashboard.
There we are.
And this was 'sales.'
So.
We have done that now for one chart.
We could very easily do that also for the
'operating profit' and the 'margin,' as you
can see on the slide.
But that is something you can do yourselves.
For each video, the file we're working on,
you can download it from there.
Even if you have skipped a file, we make sure
that every time you have a file with exactly
the right starting point to do this exercise.
So you can do it yourselves and you can try
to get the other two charts in.
So, what will be in the next video?
We have created such a chart in a vertical
position.
But we can also create it in a horizontal
And that will be the next video.
See you then!