Hello everybody!
Last time we looked at the charts to measure
the sales, operating profit, and the margin,
and they were all vertically oriented.
But of course we can do the same, but than
in stead of a column chart make a bar chart
from it.
And that's what we're going to do in the 'cost'
chart.
So let's have a look in Excel how we're going
to do that.
So, here we are in our file.
And I immediately went to the 'cost' sheet.
Here I have all the information, all the cost
elements, and the actual value, and the budget
value.
And we're going to create a chart from that.
There we are.
And then I need to do the trick with the 'ctrl'
button.
There we are.
So I've selected the data.
I've selected the cost elements, the categories,
and I've selected the numbers.
And I'm going to say 'insert', 'bar chart',
'2D bar.'
And there we are.
We know from the last time that the trick
we have to do is:
we select the actual range, we right-mouse
click.
And we're going to format that data series.
And we're going to put in on the secondary
axis.
So there we are.
We have to play a little bit with the gap
width.
We're going to change this one to 200%.
And now I want to select also the other series,
but I have to be very careful, and I don't
like that.
Luckily I can also select (over here) a different
data series.
I'm going to 'series two'.
And I will change the value over here to 50.
And this is kind of OK, but of course we have
the same scaling problem.
So, we're going to format the axes a little
bit.
And in this case I want to have a hard coded
maximum of two million.
I'm going to do the same over here.
Then, I don't need this one.
And now I have still one problem.
[Which] is that the data is not sorted correctly.
The easiest way to do that is to sort it over
here.
There are other ways to do it, but this will
do the trick.
We're going to sort it on column C, the 'actuals.'
And now it's ranked from high to low.
I like to have that in a chart.
Get rid of the title.
Get rid of the legend.
Get rid of the grid lines.
Also, I want to change these big numbers.
So we're going to change the number format
again.
And I want to have that in thousands.
So a single comma should do the trick.
There we are.
And then we have to adjust the format.
But then I have to select the chart area.
I can also change the format over here.
We want to it to be 2.15 and, our well known,
2.27.
And then we should get rid of any fill that
is left there.
No border.
No fill.
Oh, and we still have a very ugly color.
That we will change with this color.
To keep it consistent.
There we are.
And we're almost ready.
We go back to our dashboard.
And we will put it in over here.
And these are 'costs.'
And that should be a little bit larger font.
Twenty.
There we are.
Get rid of this.
And another chart filled.
So.
The cost graph is also there.
Now, let's have a look [at] what we will see
in the next video.
In the next video we're leaving the charts
behind for a moment,
and we're going to look at a full profit and
loss statement in a table.
And that is going to be interesting, I promise
you.
See you then!