Hello everybody!
And welcome back.
In contrast to the previous videos, in this
video we're not going to focus on a chart
but we're going to focus on a table.
What we see over here is a full profit and
loss statement.
When you see it you think: "well, that's easy.
That's just: we create it in Excel, copy,
paste, done."
But, we design our dashboard with a grid.
And I can promise you: that grid is
not going to match with the column layout
of this table.
Nevertheless we want to have it in.
And now you see the grid lines behind the
table, and you see what kind of mess it is.
So we have to find a solution for that.
And that solution I'm going to show you in
Excel.
So here we have our table.
If you have a look at the file yourself you
can see how we get all that information in
with the 'SUMIF's.
But what we want to do is: we want to copy
that data into our dashboard.
And that is how we start.
So I will select everything that I need.
'ctrl+c', and it is copied.
And I go to my dashboard, I position the cursor
on the right place.
In this cell, there I want to have it.
And I'm going to paste it.
But you can imagine, if I paste it.. Let's
do it, than you can see it.
If I paste it, it's going to be one ugly mess.
So we don't want to do that.
So, we do 'ctrl+z', to undo this.
We're going to select the cell, and instead
of pasting I'm now going to say 'I want to
paste it as a 'linked picture.'
And that's a very nice feature.
In previous versions of Excel it was hidden
very deep.
It was called the 'camera tool'.
But now it is on our 'paste special' menu,
and it's this option, the 'linked picture.'
And what's very nice about this is..
Here it is.
It behaves as a picture, so if we want we
could rotate it,
but it is still linked to the data.
So if I change something in the data, let's
do that, because I don't like the black negative
numbers, these should be red.
So we're going to change that.
So, over here I'm going to select all the
numeric values.
'ctrl+1' gives us the shortcut to the cell
properties.
And now I'm going to say: 'I want to have
it like this.'
But now the numbers are too big, so we have
to adjust that a little bit by saying that
we want to have them in thousands.
And the 'red' after the semicolon is telling
us that if the value if negative it should
be red.
So, if I do it like that, and I go back to
my dashboard it should be reflected in my
funny rotated linked picture.
Let's see if we can get it straight again.
There it is.
And we have to adjust the format a little
bit.
And here I use the 'alt' button again to make
sure it will move with the grid.
And then I will cheat a little bit.
And there we have our data.
And it's linked, so if any of the figures
change, the table will also change.
And what we should do is get rid of some of
the mock-up titles.
So we will remove this chart title, the chart
footer, chart title, chart footer.
And area title. And area title.
The rest we will clean up later on.
But here we have our table.
So that was something different.
Not a chart but a table.
Let's see what the next video is going to
be [about].
There we're going to work with something you
also saw in one of the earlier lectures, the
sparklines.
See you then!