Hello everybody!
In this video we're going to focus on the
sparklines.
And we combine it with a top-ten list.
Here you see a detailed [view] of it.
So, I have two top-ten lists.
I have a top-ten list of all the customers,
with their sales.
And I have a top-ten list of the product,
But they're both year-to-date figures, so
I also want to see somehow a little bit the
trend.
And for that we use a sparkline.
So let's see in Excel how we can create this.
So we're back in our file.
We need to have the two top-ten lists over
here.
And the data is prepared, of course.
Here we have our customer top-ten.
And the trick I did is that I use the top-ten
functionality of Excel, of the PivotTable.
In the filter, you can choose a top-ten.
And that's what we did.
So that means that I always have 10 values.
And then I use a lookup function, an index
function to get the data replicated over here.
So that I can paste it into my dashboard.
And I need some supporting data of the last
twelve months, for the sparklines.
So the sparklines is the first object we're
going to create.
It should go over here, so I'm going to select
the trend column.
And then I say: 'insert,' a spark.. not a
sparkline, but a column-sparkline.
And then it want's to know where the data
is located.
So the nice thing you can do with a sparkline
is that you can select a whole group.
And then you select the data that goes with
it.
There we are.
And it will create the sparklines.
And what is very nice, is that the sparklines
are now organized in a group.
So I can change the properties of the sparklines
with one step.
And I want to have a different color.
The ugly one.
There we are.
Ah.. I think for this one we can also use
this one.
So that's the sparkline.
And then we're going to treat it exactly the
same as we did with the P&L table.
I'm going to select it.
I'm going back to the dashboard.
I position my cursor.
And again I paste it as a 'linked picture.'
And I adjust the size a little bit.
There we are.
And now we have to do the same for the product
top-ten.
We select the trend column again.
We insert a sparkline.
Select the data.
Adjust the color.
And copy the table.
Back to our dashboard.
And we paste it again, as a 'linked picture.'
And as a final step we have to adjust the
size a little bit.
There we are.
So we're almost done now.
So, we're almost there.
All the charts are filled.
There is one [bit of] trouble.
There is one problem.
To the right we have a white empty place for
a legend.
And that is something you can figure out yourself
how you can copy that in.
The hint that I'll give you is that you can
also use a linked picture.
And if you look in the file, you will find
a sheet that is labeled 'legend,' where you'll
find an area that you can copy.
And the other thing you have to do is you
have to clean up the colors a little bit.
Because this is looking very ugly.
We only needed that to visualize our grid.
But this is how we would like to see it.
So we want to have some gray background behind
the graphs, and all the other colors should
go.
And we see your legend to the right.
And that brings us to the end of this series
of videos.
We have to surprises for you, two little bonuses
that you can have a look at.
But I would like to end with this slide.
That is: we spent a lot of time doing all
kinds of tricks and making a nice dashboard
in Excel.
But what is really important is that before
you start doing anything in Excel is that
you really think: "what is the information
that I need to present to the driver behind
my dashboard?"
So, I hope you enjoyed it.
I hope to see some of you back in the bonus
videos.
And otherwise, see you next time!