So in this MOOC, in all of the weeks'
videos we will use
one running example for all of the
videos
that you'll also work on in the exercises.
And for this week
we are going to think about the
spreadsheet to handle
the Stock exchange. I don't make a lot
of money as a professor, so
I have to do a little bit of investing
on the side to make ends meet.
So I have this little spreadsheet where I have
a bunch of companies that I own some
shares from,
and the number of shares that I own. And of
course, now I want to know
how is my stock portfolio doing - am I
making money on it? So what I need for
this, of course, is
recent stock information. I need to know
what the value of all the stocks is that
I have. So what I can do for that -
let me make a new worksheet and go to
the DATA tab,
and there's a button right there, maybe
you've never seen it or used it, it's
called "Get External Data".
And with this button I can get data
into my spreadsheet
from virtually everywhere. Let me
show you
how that works. So you click the button
and you select
"From Web". And what happens is that Excel
opens this little browser, just a normal
internet browser,
and I can go to any website I want. So
here I go to Yahoo Finance for the
AEX, the Amsterdam Stock Exchange, and
what you see there
is that there are little arrows in the
browser
that I can use to select what data I
want to have in my spreadsheet. So you
just click
the arrow and then you click OK, and what
you get,
where do you want your data, well just in A1
and there
is the data - right from the web into your
spreadsheet.
Isn't that cool? And this data is not a
copy-paste,
is not a static copy, because if you hit
"Refresh" you'll actually get a new
version of the website in your
spreadsheet. No coding required,
just getting the data in. So this is
nice,
what I can do now is calculate how much
money I can make on the shares that I
have in my portfolio, so let's continue.
I have the value right there, you see, this is
what my
stocks are worth. However, I can't really
calculate with them yet. Let me first get
the number of shares I have in.
So what I'll do now, I'll just copy it
from the other worksheet,
in next videos we'll definitely work on
how to connect worksheets in a better way,
but for now I'm just copying them. And
what I would like to do is - I want to
multiply the number of shares that I
have
with their value. But I can't do it, because
the Last Trade value that I get from the
web
is just the text, it's a "String" as we
call it,
and I cannot multiply it, because not
just the value is in there, but also
the the time of the Last Trade.
So I need to manipulate
my data
into being able to be calculated with. So
let me add another column
where I will try to obtain the real
value - just the first part
of the String and not the entire thing
that I cannot do anything with.
Well, what Excel has is a function called
LEFT
and that allows you for any text value
to take
a number of characters from the left. So,
what I can do now is - here I want
for this value just the first 4 characters.
and then I get my value. However, I guess
you maybe
predicted this, for the second line this
doesn't work,
because there are 5 characters and
not 4.
So, I need a little bit trickery and I
can use the FIND function for that.
What the FIND function does is: in a
given text
it looks for specific value and it gives
you the location
of that String. So you see here the space
is on the 5th
position in our String, and we can use
that in
our LEFT function. So now I'm not going
to take 4 or 5,
what I'm going to take is the location
of the space.
And then I need to deduct 1 because I
don't want to include the space, I just
want the first part.
And if I drag this formula down, you
see nicely
that I only have the value, and now I
can calculate something!
Now I can drag this cell reference
to the right, or I could also
just edit the text,
and now I have the right value for my
stock. So I know what profit I would make
if I would sell
all stocks I have for the current price
taken from the web.
So what you learn in this video is how
to use
String functions to prepare data
and this is something
you're going to encounter a lot in the
following weeks.
The data that you get from the web or
data that you download within your
company
often will not have the right form.
You get
a longer list, you get something in a
string while you wanted a text file,
so you have to do some data wrangling
before you can actually start
your calculation.