In the previous video I've shown you Pivot charts
and in this video we are going
to dive in a little bit deeper. What you can do,
for example, let me show you here
is add as many fields as you want
to the legend.
For instance if we add 'Category' we get a nice color
for every combination of product and category.
But suppose we are only interested in shoes.
We can filter this using the normal filter.
"Oh no, we are not only interested in shoes...
we want socks as well."
You see we can filter, but it is a little bit cumbersome.
Every time selecting the category
and then filter.
We can make that a lot easier by using slicers,
a really nice technique that supports exploratory
data analysis.
If you have a look with me here:
Let's right-click a category and pick
'Add as slicer', and you get a nice little control panel
for the category and you can just select
whatever category you are interested in: bras, pants, ...
Using the CTRL (or SHIFT) key you can even
select multiple categories.
As easy as that.
So let's add another slicer for color, because
ultimately of course we want to have green
socks, so we add color as well.
And there: one click for green, one click for
socks, and we have an overview in our slicers.
So without any formulas or complicated analysis
you can just select the fields you are interested in,
add a slicer and then mix and match and
see what interesting patterns emerge.