We are exploring our data today, and we are
doing that around the question:
'How many green socks did Tokyo sell on Wednesdays?'
We were already getting close in the previous video.
We had color, we had category.
One thing that is missing is the date: the Wednesdays.
So, what we could do is add a slicer.
Here you see me do it through the ribbon.
That is an alternative way to get a slicer in.
Add a slicer for date... But those are a lot of dates.
Suppose we have to get our calendar out
and see which one of those are Wednesdays.
That seems like a lot of work.
That is not something we want.
An important takeaway from this course is:
If you see that something is going to take
a lot of work, if it is like an hour of manual labor,
probably there is a smarter way to do it.
And that holds in this situation as well.
So let me show you a smarter way to select the Wednesdays.
This is not what we want. Let's delete this
horrible slicer with all the dates
and look at alternative.
So what we could do is add a formula, for weekdays.
Excel has a formula WEEKDAY, where you can
just input a date, and you get the number of
weekdays from 1 on Sunday and on.
So, this works.
However, now we are mixing formulas and data,
and that is never a good idea.
And also this weekday column is not in the
data model yet, so we would have to make a
new Pivot table including weekday.
This is no good, I don't like it.
There has to be a better way to add a field.
Well let's change that sheet name as well
because obviously 'Sheet4' is not a good name.
So what is a better way to do it?
Let's use our superpowers!
If you have done the previous MOOC, you know
about Power Pivot, which is like a Pivot table
but a lot more powerful.
Like a Pivot table with superpowers.
If you have never seen Power Pivot before,
again we will post a few links under this video.
Watch them first please, because otherwise
it can be a bit too much to be introduced
to Power Pivot in a speedy way.
So if you know it, feel free to move on with me
and have a look at how we can solve our
date problem using Power Pivot.
We can click 'Manage' here in the ribbon and
now we get the data model.
So what you see here is all our data.
Here we can add a weekday column as well
in exactly the same way as we did in Excel:
we just add a formula: =WEEKDAY.
We can use any formula out of Excel here,
and there you have it.
And you don't have to even drag down.
Power Pivot automatically updates it for all the records
ánd automatically adds it to your Pivot table.
So it is right there. You can add a slicer for it
and now we can count: Sunday, Monday, Tuesday,
Wednesday, click. Tadaa!
All the green socks in Tokyo with just three clicks.
And not only have we now calculated the green
socks in Tokyo on Wednesdays, but we have
made an interface that allows us to analyze
any color, any category, on any day of the week.
So we have prepared our self for exploratory
analysis of our data.
See you next week!