Hello everybody. Before we dive into this topic,
let me introduce myself a little bit.
My name is Bas Jansen. I work as a PhD
student at Delft University of Technology.
I am a member of the Spreadsheet Lab,
working together with Felienne.
You see my email address and my Twitter handle on
the slide, so if you want to contact me, that is possible.
Then I would like to start with the subject.
We live today in an era of big data.
Yesterday I read a very nice quote: "Millions
of dollars yearly are spent in the collection...
...of data, with the fond expectation that the
data will automatically cause the correction...
...of the condition studied. Though accurate
data and real facts are valuable, when it...
...comes to getting results the manner of presentation
is ordinarily more important than the facts themselves."
You may say 'Okay, that's a nice quote'.
But what really surprised me
is the date of this quote!
This quote is more than 100 years old.
So, actually, there is nothing new here.
Second, what I think is very important, and
I had to learn that the hard way, is...
that when it comes to getting results the manner
of presentation is ordinarily more important
than the facts themselves.
So it is not about the numbers only.
It is also about how you present them.
And although we learn in school how to write...
a report or how to give a presentation, little
attention is spent on how to display and visualise...
quantitative information.
And that is the topic of today.
So let's have a look.
One of the founding fathers, and Felienne
mentioned it also last week, is Edward Tufte.
He wrote a very nice book that I would really recommend
to read: 'The Visual Display of Quantitative Information'.
And he coined a term, he coined a definition.
That definition is the data-ink ratio.
Data-ink ratio means that it is the amount
of data-ink you use as a proportion to the total
ink that is used to print the graphic.
Maybe what would be a better representation
of that is thinking like this: It is one minus
the proportion of graphic that can be erased
without loss of data information.
Let me illustrate that with a little example.
So we have a table here, and you see that
there is a very heavy grid around every cell.
The question is: does that grid tell us anything
about the data that is in the table?
And that is not the case, so we should reduce that.
We can do that by making the grid less heavy.
But what would be even better is to remove the grid.
Every line that we see right now has a function.
We see the line under the countries. That is
telling us that the three countries belong together.
And below we see a line below the Sales person.
That is to divide the table in a header and a body.
And at the bottom, we have a Grand Total and
also there we use a line to divide it.
So now the lines are not just some paint on
the screen, but it is really useful information
that is helping us to interpret the table.
So data-ink ratio means: Do more with less.
Use as less pixels as possible to get your
message to the audience.
So, what are we doing when we are visualising data?
What we saw Felienne do in the introduction
was that immediately she went from the data
to formatting the message.
She selected the data and she clicked on create graph.
But actually she is skipping a few steps there.
Those are the steps we are focussing on today.
First, if you have data and if you
plan to say something about the data
then actually you have a goal,
otherwise you would not do that.
So, be sure for yourself what your goal is.
What do you want to tell about this data?
And then the second question is:
Who is your audience?
What is your audience like?
Are they very detailed people that want to
have the sixth digit after the decimal point?
Or are they more general people who say
'Well, just show me a graph'?
And, if I know what my goal is,
what should be my message then?
What do you want to tell?
If that is clear for me, then I can start...
thinking about how I am going to format the message.
So, when you are visualising data and when
you are visualising quantitative information...
actually we only have two tools that we can use.
That is a table or a graph.
Now, before I am going to explain
the difference for you
we have a nice little quiz for you
to think a little bit about...
when you should use a table
and when you should use a graph.
So tables, you normally use them
to look up individual values.
Think about a phone directory, that is a very
big table and you use it to look up data.
Tables are excellent for that.
Another thing that is very handy in a table is
you can really check individual values
and compare them to each other.
Tables are also very good if
you need very precise values.
Now, imagine you have some kind of dataset, where
you have kilograms and where you have speed.
Try to imagine to plot that in one graph.
That is very difficult, because you have two
different units of measures that you cannot
plot on the same axis, so you need more than
one axis, and it is very difficult to interpret the graph.
So, then a table is much easier
to understand.
And finally, if you have in your dataset data
on a summarised level, for example subtotals,
and you have the details, that is almost impossible
to represent in a graph, but it is very easy
to do it in a table.
So that is when you use a table.
Now when would you use graphs? You use graphs
if the message you want to bring to your audience...
is about the shape of the data that you have.
Is there some kind of pattern that you want to show
or some kind of trend that you want to highlight?
That is really where a graph is very useful.
And the other option is when you want to reveal
a relationship between two datasets.
Are variables correlated or not?
You can very well use a graph for that.