So in the last video we stood still by the
distinction between tables and graphs.
Now in this session we are going to focus
on the design of tables.
Actually on the structural design of tables.
There are only three types of tables.
Let's have a look at them.
The first one is the most simply one.
It is called a unidirectional table, actually
meaning it has only one dimension.
We have a sales person and we have revenue
and they are just displayed into separate columns.
Now we can make that a little bit more complicated
because it could be that we have
more than one category.
So, next to Sales person we have also Country.
Then we can organise the different
categories in some kind of hierarchy.
Now we see the sales person and within the
sales person we see the different countries and
we see the revenue he or she created there.
That is still a unidirectional table.
It is still one dimension.
It is all organised in rows, but now we have
some kind of hierarchy of the different categories.
But we could also create some kind of
a two dimensional table.
It is called a cross table or
bidirectional table.
We have the same categories. We still have
Sales person and we have Countries...
but now we have put the countries in the columns and
we get a more compact display of our dataset.
So that are the three types of tables: We
have unidirectional with one category,
we have unidirectional with several categories
but organised somehow in a hierarchy, and
we have a bidirectional table where we have
categories across the rows and across the columns.
So what about derived values?
Let's have a look at this table.
What we see is the different products
and the units we have sold.
And we see the revenue that was
generated by these products
and we also have some kind of forecast.
And then we have two columns that are actually
calculations of earlier columns.
So we have a percentage of total, and in this case
it is the percentage of total of the actual revenue,
and we have as a percentage of forecast,
which is actually the actual revenue...
as a percentage of the forecast.
Now you already can see that the way I have
to explain it, this is not really clear.
So we should not do this.
If you have derived values, if you have values
that are calculated based on other columns,
we should move these calculations...
as close to the other columns as possible.
And now you see we have moved the percentage
of total and put it next to the actual revenue.
Now it is very clear that the percentage of total
is a percentage of the actual revenue.
The same is true for the forecast.
So, that about derived values.
Now, what if you want to compare?
Here we see again the same data,
but now we want to have a difference between...
the forecast versus the revenue and
forecast versus the planned revenue.
If that is the case, it is important to have the columns
that we have to compare, that we locate them...
as close as possible to the column to compare with.
Whitespace. Now if you open your Excel spreadsheet,
and if you create your data, Excel will by
definition give you a default row height.
And that determines the amount
of whitespace you see.
Maybe you are wondering
'Why is whitespace important?'.
Whitespace helps us to determine
what is a row and what is the next row
and to distinct two rows from each other.
The more whitespace I give, the easier it is.
But of course there is a balance.
Here you see different values for the whitespace
and it is up to you to determine...
what you think is best readable.
My preference is either the 50 or the 100 percent.
It is important that you know that you have a choice
yourself that you can help the reader by...
defining the amount of whitespace
how he or she can interpret the table.
We can do that for rows, but of course
we can also do that for the columns.
That actually goes back to what
we said in the very first session:
It is all about the message.
What do I want to tell?
What do I want to give to people?
How do I want them to read my table?
Should they read it by column: column by column?
Then this would be a very good choice.
Or would it be better if they read it row by row?
What I could do then is decrease the amount
of whitespace between the columns
and increase the whitespace between the rows.
Then, people are automatically going to read
the table row by row and not column by column.
So, in this video we saw a little bit about
how to design the structure of a table.
In the next session we are going to look at
some best practices that will help us...
to create really awesome tables.