In our last session we have looked at the
structural design of tables.
But, we also prepared some little tips for
you how you can even improve your tables further.
So, let's have a look at that.
The first thing is about the grid.
Unfortunately we still see a lot of tables
that are displayed in the upper left corner
where a full grid is used.
As we said in our introduction:
We have to think about the data-ink ratio.
Are all these lines telling us something about
the data that is in the table?
That is actually not the case.
So we should try to get rid of all the lines
and keep only the lines that we really need.
That is the table in the bottom right corner.
What we see there is that we need a line...
to show you show you which three countries
belong together, we need a second line
to make a distinction between the header of the table
and the body of the table and we need a line
to make a distinction between the body of
the table and the footer of the table.
And that is all we need.
For the rest we can organize it with whitespace.
So, try to imagine that the pixels are very
expensive and try to minimize them.
Now, if you look in your Excel interface,
you can format tables.
A lot of popular formats use alternating colors
in different rows, so the first row is white,
the second row is green, the third row is
white, the fourth green and so further.
Actually, I think that is not a really good use of fill.
If you want to use fill, again, it all ties
back to your message, to your goal.
What do you want to communicate?
If I want somebody to pay attention to a single
cell in the table, then that would be a very
good use case to fill the cell, and that is
what I did in the first table. We made it red,
so it is very clear, people have to look there.
But it could also be that I want them to focus...
on a certain sales person in a certain region.
In this case, Mr Hanson in the United States.
So I used a very light fill to highlight the
row and the column and it will guide the eyes
of the reader of the table to these data.
So, I can use fill to influence how readers
are going to read my table and to help them
to understand the point I want to make.
Now some basic rules about alignment.
It is not really difficult. If it is text, you align it left.
If it are numbers, you align it right.
And then the only trouble we have with dates.
You see it at the bottom of the screen: actually,
the alignment of the date, that is not really
a problem, but the format of the date itself.
My advice would be to try to get your date in a format
that has the same length for every possible date.
Would you use a date like 'January 1, 2014',
then consider it text and do a left align.
And if it is all the same length...
then you can either use left, center or right.
You see that the wide columns in the bottom table
those are the situations you don't want to end up with.
So that about alignment.
Also, you have to think about the levels of precision.
So in the first column we see three times '2' at the
bottom three rows. But actually, it is 2.4, 2.1, 2.0.
If that is important for my message, because
that is the question: Does my reader need...
to understand that there is a difference
between these three values?
Then I need to at least show one decimal.
Making it two decimals in this case would not
be necessary, because from the 2.4, 2.1, 2.0...
the reader can already see that there is a difference.
Only if the precise value would be really necessary,
then I could increase the number of decimals.
And then we have the number format.
We see now the revenue column
and it is a bit difficult to read.
That is because there are no thousand separators.
So I always would advise
to include a thousand separator.
On the right side, you see something different.
I did not tell you when I introduced myself
but actually I am a financial guy.
Financial people really don't like negative values.
So we try to hide that a little bit by putting
a negative value between parentheses.
But the trouble… What you can see now, if
you look at the second number in the table
and compare it to the third, is that the numbers
are not aligned, because of the parentheses.
And that is something you need to fix.
You can do that, and what you would like to see is this.
The numbers are all aligned, but there is some space
around the number so put the parenthesis there.
I would really like to show you
in Excel how you can do that.
So that in an exercise you
can try that for yourself.
So here we are.
We have the same data.
I am going to select the data...
and I go to the cell properties to the number format.
Here I can see the number format and the trick.
Here we see the wrong number formatting.
We see that the alignment is not correct.
We want to change that. So if we go to the cell
properties, we go to the custom number format...
then you see here the number format
and there is a semicolon in-between.
Left to the semicolon is the positive value.
Right to the semicolon is the format of the
negative value.
And here we can see that negative values
are within parentheses.
The trick we have to do is that we have to instruct Excel
to reserve a little bit of space for these parentheses.
We can do that by entering an underscore...
and then the character that Excel
should reserve space for.
And if you do it like this... If it displays
a positive value it will ignore this, but
it will make a little bit more space, and
that is what we can see if we click on it.
So now we see that...
You can see that next to the 8 there is little room
to make sure that everything is well aligned.
So that is about the number format.
With that we end the best practices for table design.
Also we finish the chapter about tables.
In the next session we are going to look at graphs.