Welcome back! In the previous video we've
looked at
reasons why you want to use lookup
functions and that was because
direct links in spreadsheets are going
to be messed up
if you change your data on the other
side, for example, by sorting.
I really hope you have this ingrained
into your spreadsheet brain -
that if you see a formula like this, if
you see a direct link
in your own worksheets or in a spreadsheet
that your colleague has made,
for example,
try to think: is this really the best way
to organize my spreadsheet?
Am I really sure that that C2 is going
to contain the same value
if I look at the spreadsheet tomorrow?
So what can we do about this?
We can use lookup functions and those
will be explained
in this week's videos.
But first, let's take a step back and not talk
about spreadsheets for like 1 minute.
What actually does it mean
if you're looking up a value?
Let's look at that
outside of the spreadsheet context in,
well, the canonical example
of looking something up - a phone book. What
are the three ingredients that you use if
you look something up in a phone book?
Well, first of all, you have a value that
you're looking for,
in this case the name Bauer. That's what
we're looking up. The second ingredient is
what are we looking in,
in this case the phone book of
NamesandNumbers.com.
And third ingredient isn't actually
that obvious - the third ingredient of searching
is what am I going to return. In this
example we are returning
the town in which Bauer lives. And
this three ingredients are also occurring
in lookup functions in a spreadsheet.
So let's look at how that looks:
we use a formula here. First of all,
we're going to get rid
of those direct links. We will
select them and just say:
right click, Clear Contents. We don't
want to see those direct links again.
Now we have a room to import our new
formula,
the VLOOKUP. So we just type VLOOKUP
in our formula and now we input
the three ingredients for looking up:
first of all - what are we looking for.
That's the code.
Second, what are we looking in -
the ProductInfo worksheet.
And third of all, what are we going
to return:
the third column of the ProductInfo
worksheet.
And now you see - we have
associated price
with the Bench, in this case
the B809 product code.
So quick question:
is this formula perfect? Apart from
whether or not you know
the VLOOKUP function,
can you spot what actually is wrong with
this formula? I'll give you five seconds
to think about it.
It's not perfect, right? You know that
because I forgot the dollar sign ($).
If I draw this formula down now, you'll
see that the links get messed up
because I didn't input the dollar sign.
So let's fix that first.
Just delete the original reference and
add the dollar signs.
By the way, you don't have to do it
manually as I do here.
Which you can also do is select the
reference and hit
F4, and then the dollars will be
input for you. So we drag this
formula down
and now you can see it is perfect -
we're looking up
the right values. So maybe you missed what I
did here because it went a little bit
quickly.
Let's take a step back and do all
the things
step for step. All the lookup ingredients
point exactly at what they are.
So remember the three ingredients - what are
we looking for,
what are we looking in, and what are we
going to return. You see that they occur
in the VLOOKUP function as well. The
first part is what am I looking for,
this is the code. The second part is what
am I looking in,
it's this part of the ProductInfo
worksheet.
And the final argument, I would say, is
the most tricky,
because it's just a number, it doesn't
really look spreadsheety
with a reference, and it actually means
what
number of column am I going to return.
So in this case it's 3,
which means I'm returning the third
column of the whole range
that I have selected. And then you see,
with this we obtain the selling
price
for each of the codes. We can do the
exact same thing
if we also want to look up the names
associated with a certain code.
The only thing we have to change is, in
case of the names we're looking
for, the second column to return.
The rest of the formula is the same -
we're looking for the same value
in the same range. We are only returning
a different value.
With that we have made a perfect
connection between two worksheets
based on the codes that occur
in both of them.
In the next video we're going to look at
the mysterious fourth parameter of the
VLOOKUP function
that I have not yet used in this video.
See you there!