Hi! In previous videos we look at the
use of VLOOKUP,
when to use it, and, specifically, when to
use the TRUE and FALSE parameters.
Unfortunately, there's also trouble in
paradise -
The VLOOKUP function isn't always
perfect. And in this video I'm going to
show you two reasons
when you're not going to want to use
VLOOKUP.
So, if we're in a little hardware shop, but we're
only selling seven different
items using VLOOKUP is definitely
fine,
there's no problem at all. But suppose
we're running a huge hardware store
with like six thousand different
items. Then, our nice little VLOOKUP
function that you see here,
if I drag it down now, will take a long
time. You see
calculating... one Mississippi... Yup, there it is.
It's pretty slow and it would be okay
if it would
only be slow if I'm calculating
the VLOOKUP function.
But the spreadsheet will now remain slow
because the VLOOKUPs will be
calculated all the time.
For instance, probably you've noticed my typo
here - I'm not selling a Clam Hammer,
I'm selling a Claw Hammer. So if I'm
changing that
small typo, again everything has to be
recalculated.
So, using a lot, like six thousand
VLOOKUPs in the spreadsheet
is going to make my spreadsheet slow for
every operation
that I have. So, the first reason
VLOOKUPs can be cumbersome
is they're pretty slow for large datasets.
The second reason,
suppose your boss comes into your office
and she says "Hey, I want to offer a
discount today on
Claw Hammers and Rip Saws, and you need
to give me the associated codes because
I need to put those codes
into the register system for the discounts". And
you're like:
Oh, I know how to do that! I've been following
this super cool
online Excel course, I can do it! I'll
just put in the names,
that's easy - the Claw Hammer and the
Rip Saw, I will type them up.
No problem, and I'll just use
VLOOKUP
to look up the codes that go with the name.
VLOOKUP,
I know how to do it, look up the name,
go to the
information sheet... Oh...
What
column do I send back? -1?
I want to have a value that's back in
the stream.
Unfortunately, there's no such thing as
a -1 column
in VLOOKUP. The only way you can
use VLOOKUP
is this way - from the first column, and
retrieve something that's
in a later column. There's no way that you
can go back
in the stream with VLOOKUP function.
It only works
one-way! So these are two reasons that
VLOOKUP functions
aren't perfect. If you want to have speed
or if you want to have a two-way street,
you want to look up
in both directions, then, unfortunately,
VLOOKUP function is not the right
function. There's also good news -
in the next video I will show you what
functions to use
as an alternative, if you're in one of
those two scenarios. See you there!