Welcome back to EX102X.
Last week we talked about data exploration.
Looking at what happens inside your data.
But the only thing we have done last week
is look back, look into the past of what
happened to our data.
But of course using data,
we can also look into the future.
We can determine using data: Where are we
going? Are we on the right track, or should
we maybe switch and start doing something else?
And that is the topic of this week.
If you have done the exercises
this is what you ended up with last week.
And, if you have not done them, then it is
really best that you stop watching this video
right now and first do the exercise, because
it's a lot more fun if you work on data you
prepared yourself.
So using the data that you have made in the
exercise of last week, we together are going
to detect trends in the data.