So this week we are detecting trends,
and the first technique you already know
because it is conditional formatting that we used
in the previous MOOC as well.
What we did in the previous MOOC like I am
doing here is just use one threshold and visualize
what is above and below it, and you automatically
get the average here.
It shows something, but it is not exactly
what we want.
We can do more powerful things
by using color scales.
So as you see here, you get a visualization
that is wide, very much, a lot of different colors.
However, not all the visualizations are the same.
For example the second one, visualized,
this is high numbers with red
and low numbers with green.
So don't just randomly pick one. Make sure that
the colors match what you are trying to tell.
So this gives us an indication of the data.
You see that high values are very green, however
it is a bit unfair to compare pants and socks
because socks are just a lot cheaper.
So it would be more fair if we have one color scale
per product category, and we can do that.
Let's remove this and add a new coloring.
So we pick one range and then we add the scales
and that means it is scaled over only that range.
So a high value in pants might get a different
color than a high value in socks if they are
the same value.
So this already gives us an idea of the data.
Isn't that nice? We start to see some trends.
For example bras were selling quite well early
in the season, and now doing a little bit less,
whereas socks had a slow start, but
now seem to be greener and greener.
With a few clicks, a few conditional formatting rules
we already get some idea about our data.
But there are lots of other things we can
do with conditional formatting as well.
One thing that I really like is the Top 10 feature,
where you just get a visualization
of what is doing best. Especially if you
have lots of products, that is nice.
You can also add data bars, which is like
a mini-chart within your data.
And finally there are icon sets, where you
can click circles or stop signs
instead of coloring the cell.
One thing I want to point your attention to
is these arrows, they are called 'directional'.
You might think that they are visualizing a trend.
But they are not!
They are exactly equal to the circles.
They just give an up arrow for a high value
and a down arrow for a low value.
They are not actually representing a trend.
So be aware, if we are trend plotting
don't accidently use the arrows, unless you are
actually calculating a difference.