This week is all about detecting trends.
In the previous video we used conditional formatting,
added colors to our data to get
a sense of what products are doing best.
However there is a risk in using colors.
Some people are color blind and they might
be very bad at distinguishing red from green.
And also some people might think it is visually
not very attractive to have lots of colors
on a spreadsheet, and there is some sense in that.
So in this video I am going to show you an alternative way of quickly exploring your data.
And this way is called spark lines and it
was designed by a man called Edward Tufte.
He is like the godfather of data visualization.
Below the video we will put a few links to
a few of his books that are really really great.
If you want to learn more about how to visualize
your data in a concise but beautiful way,
I can really recommend these books.
So one of the things he invented is called
sparklines and it is now embedded into Excel.
So we want to make a spark line for this and
normally I would place it on the bottom, there.
But because I don't have room on my screen
for this time I am going to put the spark
lines next to the data.
So I am just going to copy the header.
And what I do then is I am going to go to
'Insert' and 'Insert a line'.
It is not called 'spark line' but just 'line',
a little bit misleading.
So we select the data that we want and there:
BAM! We get a nice tiny little graphic showing
the flow of the data, the trend of the data.
And you see the top right there, on the top
of the graph is the same as the green cells
that we had before.
We can even select 'High point' (in the ribbon) and
then you get a marker.
Like a formula we can drag these spark lines
and then we automatically get it for 'pants'
and 'shoes' and 'socks' and for the total.
You see for socks there we have the top right
there as we have the top in the data.
So, it is a really nice way to look at your data.
And like with conditional formatting, there
are lots of different options that you can use.
For example you can change them into
a column bar instead of a trend, which is also nice.
I think it is a bit harder in
this situation to see the trend
but it is a lot easier to see where the high points are.
There is one other option: 'Win/Loss'.
I am not going to talk about that
because that is what you will be doing in the exercises.