Hello eh, hello Miss Kiers.
Thank you so much for taking the time...
to have a Skype meeting with me today.
Yes. Who are you, please?
So, I'm Felienne.
I am an intern in your hotel.
I have been working here for a few weeks,
and eh...
No one seems really to have a good idea of
what is going on in the hotel.
Like, how many night we usually sell,
how many people are there.
Everything is fine in the hotel.
- Yeah I know, I know, it's great.
But I just took this course on Data Analysis
and I thought maybe if we look into the data
of the hotel we can learn a bit more about
exactly is going on.
Well, I'm not sure if that is necessary.
But if you really want to,
I can ask Gretta to send you some files.
That would be very very much
appreciated, if you could...
Thank you Felienne.
Thanks, bye.