Hello again, Miss Kiers, this is Felienne.
I have looked at all the data, but I think...
we might be missing something, because, every
Wednesday I see clowns in the hotel.
But the clowns are not in my data, so could it
be possible that you didn't send me all the data?
Maybe Gretta missed something.
I suggest you stop this crazy hobby, Felienne.
You are just looking around in the hotel
finding all kinds of eh... data you're missing.
I think this is a waste of your time.
But... [SIGH] If you really want,
I can add the data of the service providers.
Thank you, thank you. That would be nice.
Then I could do some analysis into
if the services are really...
making us money.
Thank you so much.
Gretta will send it, as soon as she can.
Thanks! See you.
- Bye, bye.