In a previous video we looked at array
formulas.
More specifically, we've looked at how to
transpose our data
so that we can filter it for questions
that we don't want to have in an exam anymore.
Our data is prepared now, it's in the
right way.
So let's filter it, we can go to the filter
button, select our data
and say: Hey we don't want all the data,
we don't want all of the questions
we only want to have everything
beside the second row. But unfortunately
we still have the same result, because we
have transposed
everything including the last column
which is now the last row, so don't worry
you think,
we can just delete it. That doesn't work,
you cannot change part of an arrayformula.
It's impossible once you have selected
an area
that's meant for an array, you cannot
delete cells in it.
And this is a good, because you don't
want to accidentally overwrite part of
your array
by hitting the keyboard with your elbow.
But in this case,
we don't want to have the final column
anymore, we want to add new calculations,
So what we need to do is use the same
region again but we with one row less and put
the
array formula in again. So
the only way we can delete the values is:
delete everything,
delete the entire array formula and then
paste it again
using one row less. It's a bit cumbersome
so if you want to change an array you have
to change everything.
But there we have it. So now we can add the
SUM() function ourself,
based on the transposed data. We just
add a SUM()
of the entire column. There we go, no
worries.
And we drag it.
Yep, there it is.
So now we can filter, we are entirely
prepared, we go to filter we remove
the second question from the list of
questions,
and it works. Apparently, it doesn't.
The calculation even though a row is
filtered out,
is still calculating on the entire
column. so we can not use a function to
filter, because it will still
calculate the entire column unfortunately.
I hope you're screaming right now, I
really hope
that on the other side of the video you
are saying this:
Hey, but I know why this isn't working
because formulas are
not for analysis, formulas are for
calculation
if you want to do analysis you
should do something else.
For instance a pivot table,
indeed. Okay, okay, okay, I hear you.
Let's try to do our analysis with a pivot
table. We get rid of the formulas
they are not for analysis. We get rid of
the filter and we select all the data
and put it
into a pivot table. Filter
can go, we select all the data.
Oh yeah, I've changed the student number
to one two three four instead of
the very long student numbers, because
that will make the pivot table a bit too big.
Let's go, we add pivot table. Yep, there we go.
select the pivot table and we put
it on a new worksheet that I have just
made.
Select the data and we have a pivot table.
So now we can filter right? We can say we
want all of the students, these are student
numbers now,
all the sums of all the students.
Click, click, click.
Yep and we can add a filter
on what questions to use, super easy if
you've seen the week
about the pivot tables, you know how to do
this. We can just select
what questions we want. However as you
see, it's pretty hard to compare the
different scenarios with each other.
Now this is 55 if I change a value
it changes, but what I would like to have
is have the
scenarios side by side. One row for
the exam with question 2 included and
one row
for the exam without question 2, without
everything
swapping all the time. If I do that
the only way I could do that is to make
two pivot tables with two different
filters.
And then of course we're running into
the duplication problem again.
There's another downside of using
pivot table for this analysis,
if we go to the table field settings down
here,
there's a limited number of functions we
can use.
So there is SUM(), AVERAGE(), MIN(), MAX(), but not
all of Excel's I think 350+
built-in functions are there.
There's a limited set a functions that we
can use. So if we're summing the exam
results that's fine,
but if we want take differeent quartals for instance,
if we want to use the median
if we want to use the mode, then
there's no way that we can do that with
a pivot table.
So in conclusion, yes formulas are for
calculation and not for analysis,
however there are some limitations to
what you can do
with pivot tables, because they don't
support everything and also they don't
really support
scenario analysis in which I want to
compare two different filters with each
other.
And that's where you're going to need
array formulas.